is it important to investigate and try
to understand other world views or
philosophical stances
is there benefit in trying to see why
wrong views are wrong and how far should
one go with this investigation
yeah well i think that's that's really
the question you want to ask that's it
how far
uh it can be some benefit
say for somebody who's is not absolutely
has no inclination to to mentally
clarify anything it could encourage some
discernment discrimination on that right
level uh but uh but
but
yeah more often than not it's it's probably
more often than not it's it's probably
gonna be if you go too far it's gonna be
just a waste of time
it's going to be revolving around
satisfying your mental craving for
mental clarity and
and views
the point is even if you do investigate
these things
you do so just so you're a step closer
to uproot your suffering
not to have a you know a satisfying
standpoint so you
so you
you really don't want to go too fast so
if you recognize yourself as someone who
has a tendency to go there then you
probably shouldn't do any of it if you
recognize yourself as somebody who
doesn't want to think about any other
views then maybe you should
just to challenge your own views to see
whether you actually understood
something or you're just
complacent about it because you never
challenge what what your understanding
is if there is any
because there's so many different views
and that's it's like a non-never-ending
it is a never-ending journey
i mean if you if you're yeah if your
goal is to address
every wrong view well
you're never going to finish that work
so in other words if you do go into
exploring never lose the context as to why you're
never lose the context as to why you're
doing it for the sake of your own
freedom from suffering and understanding
not for the sake of you know
developing superior standpoints and so
on
if that happens that's a side effect
winning battles
oh yeah it's definitely not about that okay
okay
now the second question
relates to this suitor
that i'll read on
because there are these three kinds of
suffering what three
what three
suffering due to pain suffering due to
sankaras formations activities
activities determinations
suffering and suffering due to change so so
dukkha
suffered suffering due to pain
sankara dukata suffering due to
sankata's formations
suffering due to change
there are these three kinds of suffering
the noble eightfold path is to be
developed for direct knowledge of these
three kinds of suffering for the full
understanding of them for the utter
destruction and for their abandoning so
so
i believe the person wanted to know
does the you know
if one becomes an arahant
is all these sufferings gone
no suffering is gone on account of all
these things not all these things are
gone so pain
so pain
pain is not gone change is not gone
sankatas are not gone
suffering on account of it is gone
so
how much of a pain will be painful when
you don't suffer an account of it how
much of a change would be painful when
you don't suffer an account of it and
how much cencadas would be causing you
discomfort when you don't suffer on
account of it well become another and
you'll see
yeah it's kind of
if you're not
if you're not even close to becoming an
adult yeah you can't even theoretically
grasp it correctly because if you do you
would be at least a sort of partner
understanding what freedom from
suffering is
so so the point is it's not
there is no change or there's no sankara
there is no bodily discomfort and pain
left for another hand he says there's no
suffering when kind of
because that's what it says these three
types of suffering have three basis on
account of which a suffering can
manifest for a mind that hasn't developed a noble
for a mind that hasn't developed a noble
later path that's it
develop the noble later path suffering
cannot manifest on account of any of the
basis of three bases of suffering
because like the the other hunt
the arahants declaration
at the end of some suitors which is
there's just this
yeah this body what suffering has left
it's on the account of this body until
it breaks apart that's the only
suffering i endure till i
go into part in ibana basically
basic discomfort yeah the the remnant
this body is the remnant of the previous
stuff and until it sort of exhausts
itself and dies there will be some
burden discomfort nuisance on account of it but
discomfort nuisance on account of it but
none of that is a base for mental
suffering he's freed
and he knows that
that's why he will dwell happily in
hibana here and now with this
you know body that's that's about to
break apart
could you describe the difference
between chitta
chitta
and dhamma in terms of satipatana
those two terms in sati
so practically speaking
cheetah is found
where you feel
dhamma as a phenomena is found where you
think where the mental activity is so
so
chitta is on the level of
pretty much
your attitude towards pleasant
unpleasant and neutral
that's where chitta is
in their broadest
sense mano is
mano is
mano and dhamma is literally what your
mind revolves around
diamonds are what you're thinking
thoughts which might be on account of
what you're feeling
but chitta is the the kind of the
attitude the underlying attitude towards
what you're feeling
something you're not explicitly thinking
in terms of phenomena
so as i said like you know overall mood
is where you look for cheetah
what what your mind revolves around
that's where these damage are
so yes you have to take care of the
these things equally
make sure you're not acting out of your
moods but then make sure don't just let
your mind revolve around dumbers that
are not suitable you just
you just
you know be aware of
the mood
well yeah be aware of the motive if
there is a version towards the
displeasure don't cultivate the aversion
if there is elation delights towards
pleasure don't cultivate it don't act
out of it if there is kind of indolence
towards the neutral just want to go you
know distract yourself sleep don't give
in to that either that's working on
chitta pretty much
and uh so how do you not give in to a
version of cheetah towards what you're
feeling well by not accepting the
dharmas of angry kind that your mind
revolves around
how do you not give in to the delight of
chitta towards pleasure pleasure and
pleasurable prospects by not accepting
the damage of sensuality
then the mind revolves around
but not daydreaming
i know daydreaming yeah when you're
bored or distracted